Renan

☐ contact@renansouza.org <u>⊗</u> |D: x9t36ewAAAAJ Updated on September 27, 2023 ❖ RenanSouza.org 🗘 renan-souza in renansouza1

Bio

evolution of Artificial Intelligence systems in HPC and cloud. science in Latin America. He researches large-scale data management techniques to support the and honored mention for the best Ph.D. thesis awards from SBBD, the main conference on data scientist and software engineer at IBM Research. He has been working as a software engineer scientist at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory. Before that (2015–2022), he was a research During his Ph.D., he was a visiting researcher at Inria, France. He received the best M.Sc. thesis Missouri State University and was an intern at Stanford University in the SLAC National Laboratory researcher, and tech lead on several projects since 2010. During his B.Sc., he spent a year at from the Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ). Since 2022, he has been a staff Renan Francisco Santos Souza holds a Ph.D., M.Sc., and B.Sc (2009–2019) in Computer Science research

Research Interests

Data Analytics • High Performance Computing in Clusters and Clouds • Machine Learning Large-scale Data Science and Data Engineering • Parallel Workflows • Data Provenance • Big

Education

o Ph.D. in Computer Science, Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Supervised by Marta Mattoso (COPPE/UFRJ) and Patrick Valduriez (Inria) Sep 2015 I Dec 2019

Title: Supporting User Steering in Large-scale Workflows with Provenance Data O Visiting Ph.D. Student, Inria/Univ. Montpellier, France

Supervised by Patrick Valduriez (Inria). Jan 2019 – Mar 2019

o M.Sc. in Computer Science, Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Supervised by Marta Mattoso (COPPE/UFRJ). Jan 2013 - Jul 2015

Title: Controlling the Parallel Execution of Workflows Relying on a Distributed Database

 Computer Science exchange student, Missouri State University, U.S. Jun 2011 - Jun 2012

0 B.Sc. in Computer Science, Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Supervised by Maria Luiza Machado Campos (DCC/UFRJ). Jan 2009 - Dec 2012

Title: Linked Open Data Publication Strategies: An Application in Network Performance Data

Technical Degree in Information Systems, Lemos de Castro

Jan 2005 – Dec 2007

Experience

0 Oak Ridge National Laboratory Research Scientist, HPC Workflows, Data & Al

Knoxville, United States Oct 2022 -Present

large-scale data science and Artificial Intelligence systems to support scientific discovery. Part of the Workflows and Ecosystem Services group, working with software research and engineering of

o IBM Research

Apr 2015 - Oct 2022 Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Research Scientist, Cloud & Al Data Management

As a Staff Research Scientist (since 2021), he led R&D projects in large-scale data science and data engineering to support Artificial Intelligence systems running on hybrid cloud and cluster environments with highly distributed and heterogeneous applications, data, and users. He develops software and do applied research to solve problems in different industries, such as energy, financial, physics, and cheminformatics.

As a Research Software Engineer (2015–2021), he participated in several R&D projects with clients in the energy field by developing techniques and systems for large-scale data integration of AI systems running on clusters and clouds. He also led the Cloud DevOps team to develop conversational AI systems.

As a Software Engineering intern (2015), he designed and implemented big data and machine learning solutions to analyze streaming social data.

SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory, Stanford Univ. Research Software Engineering intern

May 2013 – Dec 2014 Menlo Park, United States

Developed a project to build a cloud platform that uses semantic web, big data, and data warehousing techniques to store, retrieve, visualize, and publish structured data about internet performance worldwide, enabling a rich understanding of information about the Internet quality around the world.

CAPGov COPPE/UFRJ Software Engineer

Dec 2011 - Sep 2014 Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

As a lead software engineer (2013–2014), he led the development of a system that helped the Brazilian population to have easy access to information about public services provided by the Federal Government. He also participated in the development of a system to publish linked open data of the Brazilian Federal Register ("Diário Oficial da União") on the semantic web using agile methodology, ontology data modeling, and natural language processing.

As a Software Engineering intern (2011–2013), he participated in several R&D web systems for the Brazilian Federal Government.

Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro Software Engineering intern

Jan 2010 - Jul 2011 Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Developed a system to integrate data warehouse environments with structured and unstructured data to enable more intelligent and flexible information reports.

Petrobras

May 2007 – May 2008

IT Intern

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Helped to implement features and provided maintenance for web systems to support Petrobras employees.

Technical Knowledge

- O Languages: Python, Java, C, C++, Shell scripting, NodeJS, Scala, Lua
- o Relational DBMS: PostgreSQL/PostGIS, DB2, DashDB, MySQL, MySQL Cluster, MS SQL Server
- NoSQL DBMS: MongoDB, AllegroGraph, Jena, Blazegraph, Virtuoso, Sesame, Cloudant, CouchBase, Redis, Impala, Elasticsearch, HBase, Hive, Apache Ignite
- Heterogeneous Data Management: Data Integration, Multi-database Queries, Polystores, Foreign Data Wrappers
- Big Data Frameworks: Apache Spark: RDD, DataFrames, Streaming, MLib, GraphX, GraphFrames;
 Dask; Hadoop Ecosystem
- Message Brokers: Kafka, RabbitMQ
- Data Science/ML Technologies: Pandas, Jupyter Notebooks, Numpy, Matplotlib, Tensorflow, ScikitLearn, Keras, PyTorch, MLFlow, Airflow
- O Big Data Cluster Deployment: YARN, Mesos, Standalone deployment
- Business Intelligence: MS SQL Server BI developer studio, Pentaho Solutions, Talend;
- Semantic Web Tools/Languages: OWL, RDF, SPARQL, Protege
- Distributed and Concurrent Programming: PubSub, MPI, OpenMP, CUDA, Data-centric distributed and parallel programming

- O Cloud and Cluster computing: VMs, Dockers, Kubernetes, OpenShift, HPC Clusters
- O DevOps: Containers, Kubernetes, OpenShift, CI/CD Pipelines, GitHub, GitHub Actions, Travis, Jenkins
- Web Development: Python Flask/UWSGI, Java EE, Tomcat/JBoss, Spring Boot

Selected Publications

For complete list, visit: RenanSouza.org/publications

- [1] R. Souza, T. J. Skluzacek, S. R. Wilkinson, M. Ziatdinov, R. F. Silva, "Towards lightweight data integration using multi-workflow provenance and data observability," in *IEEE International Conference on e-Science*, 2023. DOI: 10.1109/e-Science58273.2023.10254822. [Online]. Available: https://doi.org/10.1109/e-Science58273.2023.10254822.
- [2] **R. Souza**, V. Silva, A. A. B. Lima, D. Oliveira, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Distributed inmemory data management for workflow executions," *PeerJ Computer Science*, vol. 7, pp. 1–30, 2021. DOI: 10.7717/peerj-cs.527. [Online]. Available: https://peerj.com/articles/cs-527/.
- [3] R. Souza, L. G. Azevedo, V. Lourenço, E. Soares, R. Thiago, R. Brandão, D. Civitarese, E. Vital Brazil, M. Moreno, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, R. Cerqueira, M. A. S. Netto, "Workflow provenance in the lifecycle of scientific machine learning," *Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience*, vol. e6544, pp. 1–21, 2021. DOI: 10.1002/cpe.6544. [Online]. Available: https://doi.org/10.1002/cpe.6544.
- [4] R. Souza, V. Silva, J. J. Camata, A. L. G. A. Coutinho, P. Valduriez, M. Mattoso, "Keeping track of user steering actions in dynamic workflows," *Future Generation Computer Systems*, vol. 99, pp. 624–643, 2019, ISSN: 0167-739X. DOI: 10.1016/j.future.2019.05.011. [Online]. Available: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.future.2019.05.011.

Grants and Awards

 2nd IBM Patent Plateau (8+ patents submitted to USPTO) 	2021
 SBBD Honored Mention for the Best Ph.D. Thesis Award 	2021
 1st IBM Patent Plateau (4+ patents submitted to USPTO) 	2020
 SBBD Best M.Sc. Thesis Award 	2017
 SBBD Honored Mention on the paper 	
Spark Scalability Analysis in a Scientific Workflow	2017
o CAPES M.Sc. Grant	2013 - 2014
Brazil Science Mobility Grant - Missouri State University	2012 - 2013
 Scientific Initiation Grant - Federal Univ. of Rio de Janeiro 	2010

Badges and Certifications

Machine Learning Specialist Professional
 Course duration: 73h — 2022

 Exploratory Data Analysis, Regression, Classification, Deep Learning, Reinforcement Learning, Unsupervised Learning, Time Series and Survival Analysis, AI Ethics and Explainability

○ Trustworthy AI and AI Ethics Course duration: 3.5h — 2022

• Enterprise Design Thinking Practitioner 2022

LinkedIn Skill Assessment: Python, MySQL, Linux, T-SQL, NoSQL

Languages

- English Full proficiency
 - Missouri State University, U.S.
 Duration: 150h Jun 2012 Aug 2012
 Scientific English for Graduate Students
 - Cultura Inglesa (English Culture), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
 2001 2009
- Portuguese Native
- Spanish Fluent reading, intermediate speaking and understanding, limited writing